A few years after
An Lushan rebelled against the Tang
the dynasty's western borders lay undefended.
The Tubos went on the warpath.
Late winter,
the first year of Emperor Daizong's reign.
FORT YUNSHAN, SICHUAN
GAO SHI, SOUTHWEST SICHUAN GOVERNOR
Governor Gao!
Our main forces are on their way.
You people of this little fort
are all going to die.
Abandon the fort.
Retreat to Lushui Pass.
LUSHUI PASS
Governor Gao!
The Emperor has fled the capital?
Yes.
His Majesty is in Shanzhou.
The Tubos have besieged Chang'an.
Marshal Guo Ziyi's army -
where are they?
Still in Lantian.
More ministers and generals have been executed.
His Majesty is resolute.
As soon as he took the throne
he executed Li Fuguo and Chancellor Yuan.
These are turbulent times.
The court has sent a flurry of orders
urging Your Excellency to lead your army
to attack the Tubo troops in the west-
forcing their main army to turn back
and lift the siege of Chang'an.
Instead, I abandoned Yunshan
and retreated to Lushui Pass.
General Yan Wu will soon take over.
But
you, sir, are still in charge
of the Southwest Sichuan Command.
Of course
when the court assigns blame
I'll be the guilty one.
Bring the Tubo prisoner for interrogation.
You must answer truthfully.
Reporting!
Governor
dozens of cavalry are at the camp gates.
It's extremely urgent.
Says he's an Imperial Envoy, Military Inspector.
Military inspector?
Imperial Envoy?!
Go to the gates.
Inspect their credentials.
Receive them courteously.
Yes sir.
It's Heaven's Will!
Take the Tubo away.
Chain him up outside the tent.
Yes sir.
Get up! Move!
Governor Gao!
Someone, help!
IMPERIAL GUARD LIEUTENANT
Governor!
Inspector Cheng.
For not riding out to greet you
I apologise.
The Emperor sent me west
to ask you some questions, sir.
Please answer them all.
If you cover up anything, sir
or are less than clear
I am authorised
to execute you
and punish your entire clan.
I was about to kill myself for failing the emperor.
Ask, sir,
and I'll say all I know.
Li Bai.
Li Bai?
Li Bai. Li Taibai.
Imperial Scholar.
Calls himself Green Lotus Hermit.
Li Bai.
Li Bai?
You're not here about the Tubos?
How did you meet Li Bai?
Start from the beginning.
He was...
he was once my good friend.
We bonded over poetry.
All people of the Tang write poetry
from His Majesty down to peddlars.
What's special about that?
Sunset's clouds color a twilit sky
Geese ride the North Wind through falling snow.
Don't fear loneliness on the road ahead
For who in this world doesn't know you?
I've heard that poem before.
I wrote it when I was thirty.
as a farewell to Dong Da.
I was so young and ignorant!
Even if everyone knows you
( Poetry of the Rivers and Mountains )
how many count as true friends?
So if Li Bai was once your true friend,
why, five years ago,
did you seek to destroy him?
Governor !
We met when we were young.
I was twenty.
It was near Dongting Lake.
We met
when he tried to kill me.
I'd left home for the first time.
I'm from the Gao clan of Bohai.
The 35th boy in my generation.
They called me "Gao Thirty-Five".
My grandfather served Emperor Gaozong
as Northeast Commander.
He crushed the Turks and Goguryeo.
He was buried next to Emperor Gaozong's tomb
and made Prince of Bohai.
GAO SHI AS A YOUTH
( GAO CHONGWEN)
My father had great expectations of me.
He hoped that one day
I'd be like my grandfather
flying the banner beyond the Great Desert.
Confucius said
"To practice what you learn
But learning to read
was really difficult for me.
When I looked at a book
the characters swam on the page like tadpoles.
racing around, just a big mess.
"Do you do your utmost to help others?"
Father
F-forgive me.
The Gao Spear has a worthy heir.
My father was a warrior-scholar.
But when he died, in Shao, Guangdong,
He was but a minor official of a minor county.
I was sixteen. My mother had long passed away.
Father managed his affairs poorly. We had nothing.
I took his ashes from Guangdong back to Guangling
I came home to an empty house.
I was left all alone in the world.
After three years of mourning
I left home for the capital, Chang'an.
I didn't read well but I had martial skills.
It was Kaiyuan, the Tang's Golden Age.
I would go straight to Chang'an,
GAO SHI
serve the Emperor,
make my name
and restore the glory of my family.
I didn't expect travel to be so hard.
I rode west from Guangling.
After almost a month
I'd only reached Dongting Lake
and my money was running out.
Outta the way!
Thief!
Stop!
Damn thief. You're skilled.
But you're no hero up on that horse.
If you're a true fighter, dismount.
We'll see who wins then!
S-sir, who are you calling a thief?
You steal my horse and bags and you're no thief?
You're good at this, thief.
To block my sword isn't easy.
But with such skill, why thieve?
J-just now two horses galloped past.
They had saddlebags.
I think they were your thieves.
If you're not a thief
why do you wear the same hat?
Oh! A c-coincidence.
Okay, I believe you!
Lend me your horse!
My horse!
You're quite the warrior.
Thank you for saving me.
Earlier, I falsely accused you.
I beg your pardon.
No n-need to apologise.
The law of the Tang
says if a civilian meets a thief
killing him isn't a crime.
Otherwise, I couldn't have helped you.
Y-you know a lot about the law!
B-brother, don't mock me.
So young, and yet so formal.
Thank you.
Li Bai, at your service.
LI BAI
Gao Shi, at yours.
Gao Shi, lucky you lent me your horse.
If I didn't catch them, I'd never forgive myself.
- What you're carrying - it's valuable?
I wouldn't care if it was gold or silver.
But this
This is my dear friend Wu Zhinan.
Brother Wu meet Brother Gao.
This is...?
We studied together in our youth.
After I left Sichuan I ran into him at Mt Lu.
We looked for a Taoist master together.
But fate was cruel.
Three years ago, he took ill and died.
I made a pledge
to take his remains somewhere beautiful
and bury him there.
These are his remains?
That's right!
I'll bury him by Yellow Crane Tower.
Let that famous tower be his companion.
A marvellous idea, right?
Come, Brother Gao
Come with me. Let's go!
I'd never met anyone like him.
He said his family was from Longxi.
A 19th generation descendent of Li Guang
related to the imperial clan.
He used to live in Sichuan
but was wandering the land, courting officials
in the hope one would recognise his talent
and commend him to the court
so he could serve the country.
Here you go!
Enjoy!
Brother Gao
we've got time.
How you killed that thief with your spear
it was like a flying dragon.
If you'll teach me spear fighting
I'd be happy
to teach you
the art of wrestling. Say yes?
Let's do it.
The Way of wrestling
is to answer force with feints
distract to attack
and rely on variation.
The key
is to trick your opponent.
It's too easy to see through you.
Gao Shi-
know how to trick an opponent?
When I was eighteen
I went to Mt. Changping
to study strategy with a Master Zhao.
I never mastered strategy
but I did learn Master Zhao's
art of beckoning the birds.
There's a North Sea fish
That's called the Kun
It transforms into a bird
That's called the Eagle
Li Bai.
I'd never met anyone like him.
So free in spirit.
He lived in this world
but seemed apart from it as well.
Got it!
Brother Gao
Living in such a golden age as this
we shall be Great Eagles!
JIANGXIA YELLOW CRANE TOWER
The yellow birds flit
And perch upon the jujube tree.
Whilst cruel fate
steals the life of a good man.
"Here lies Wu Zhinan"
The Great Eagle never spread its wings
dying young and far from home.
O grief! O sorrow!
Brother Wu
O grief!
O sorrow!
Brother Gao
life is like the morning dew.
Blink and it's gone.
So tragic.
One day I'll devote myself to the Tao.
I'll discover the path
to immortality.
Brother Li
"Confucius never speaks of the occult."
The Tao of Immortality
is too.. too illusory.
Brother Gao
Nothing in life is easy.
In my time in this world
I want to do the hardest things.
One day
I'll prove myself.
Make a name.
Become a hermit, find the Tao.
But before I can do that
I must achieve official rank.
I've heard that the governor here
has a great eye for talent.
Brother Gao
you've heard of "Passing the Scroll"?
Of course.
This governor loves essays.
I wrote "Ode to the Great Eagle" for him.
He'll promote me for sure.
The dynasty has a system for promoting talent.
Officials of high rank
were responsible for recommending talent.
So literati presented their best work
to prominent officials
to get recognition.
It was a shortcut to official rank
It was called "Passing the Scroll".
But...
How can such shortcuts
be open to those of humble birth?
The Tang soldiers are terrified.
You've seen that.
Gao Shi has been relieved of his command.
Once the Tubo army arrives
they'll take Lushui Pass, easy.
We're also northern tribesmen.
We won't die for them.
Your army must act fast.
Yan Wu takes command in two days.
Yan Wu?
Yan Wu is coming back?
Yes! You know how strong he is.
We have to do this before that!
When the army arrives
we'll open the gates.
The tribesman are all prepared.
Understood!
But Li Bai
naturally didn't think that doors
wouldn't open for him.
JIANGXIA COUNTY GOVERNOR'S RESIDENCE
Brother Li-
I'll wait here for you.
Brother Gao, come with me!
No need to wait outside.
This governor
I've never been introduced.
Our families have no ties either.
Brother Gao
my talent
is superior to a thousand introductions
and a million years of ties.
I'm going.
Please go away.
The governor is tied up with official business.
He can't see you.
Has he read my essay?
Your father was a merchant?
Yes.
He was a trader
with businesses in Jinling and Yangzhou.
The descendant of a pedlar
and you dare to "Pass the Scroll"?
He has eyes but cannot see!
Blind!
Brother Gao! Let's go.
To argue with such an ignoramus
is below us.
Let's go to Yellow Crane Tower for a drink.
What do you say?
Let's go, Brother Gao!
That's how I learned
Li Bai was the son of a merchant.
By the laws of our dynasty
even a wealthy merchant belongs to the lower class.
The son of a merchant
can't even take the civil service exam.
C'mon, Brother Gao!
To get an official position
he had to "Pass the Scroll" and find a patron.
- But wasn't this
- One day the Great Eagle will rise
- even a harder road?
And ride the wind
- His genius could light the dark.
- for ten thousand miles.
His brilliance was obvious.
YELLOW CRANE TOWER
But I'd never met anyone
so childishly innocent as well.
Waiter! Come!
Coming!
Bring us your best wine.
Sure thing!
Brother Gao bottoms up!
Brother Gao, come, quick.
See the Yangtze?
It flows from my hometown.
Endless waters, countless peaks
this river brought me here.
Brother Gao, does your home have great rivers too?
Bohai has the Yellow River.
I've yet to see the Yellow River.
But I know the poem "Upon Stork Tower"
The sun rests on the peak before it fades
The Yellow River flows towards the sea
Wang Zhihuan's wonderful poem.
Waiter! Waiter!
Coming!
What can I do for you, sir?
I'm overcome with inspiration.
I want to dedicate a poem to Yellow Crane Tower.
Where are your poetry boards?
Ah, sir, you write poetry?
Of course.
Sir,
do you have official rank, then?
I'll have one soon, it's in reach!
Sir, why don't I bring you more dishes?
Writing poetry is so demanding.
Stop stalling. Take me to the poetry boards.
Alright.
C'mon.
Our tower has a long history.
For centuries, guests have left poems here.
Just look around, sir.
A fine place.
Waiter, of all the poems here
which is the best one?
I will write one next to it.
- Who's this person?
- To date the best one...
- Judging from his clothes,
a commoner.
I'm not so learned
but visitors all agree
it's one written just two years ago.
Just two years ago?
It's by Master Cui Hao.
He's from the Cui clan of Boling.
The Cuis are first among the Six Great Clans.
Young Master Cui
passed the civil service exams at nineteen.
Enough. Give me a brush.
Your brush.
This one, right?
He was inspired after drinking.
His calligraphy is marvelous too
it's all marvelous!
The Ancient rode off on the Yellow Crane
Leaving but an empty Yellow Crane Tower here
The Yellow Crane, gone, never to reappear
White clouds drift past, year after year
The trees of Hanyang, the sparkling stream
On Parrot Isle, grasses lush and green
Dusk sets in, where is my home?
Mist and waves, a melancholy scene.
Wonderful, really wonderful.
Such great talent!
Master Cui is young elegant, high-born
and so talented too.
Where did those two dolts come from?
Youthful ignorance, that's all.
They're still a pair of dolts.
Brother Gao
You go west to Chang'an, I go east to Yangzhou.
Today we part ways.
One day
I'll write Yellow Crane Tower's best-ever poem.
Brother Gao, let's make a date.
In a year, whether you succeed in Chang'an or not
you must visit me in Yangzhou!
I'll show you the wonders by its famous bridges
and its beauties too.
Next year, I'll visit for sure.
I touch my sword.
I raise my eyes.
Like stones in clear water, I shall be seen.
Gao Thirty-five-
That splendid talent of yours
will one day burst forth from your heart.
I take off my cap
We share a smile
We drink wine
And I sing for you.
Chang'an...
It was my first time there.
CHANG'AN
Oh, I do beg your pardon!
'To govern, first put your own house in order."
Roll call.
Wang Changling?
- Chang Jian! Chang Jian?
- Here, here!
- Raise your hands. Turn around.
- Оkay.
I said turn, how hard is that?
Is it so hard to understand?
Now get your butt back into line.
I was a poor student, I'd never pass.
At least I avoided this humiliation.
Aside from the exams
there was another path.
The emperor could test and appoint you himself.
He's discerning and looks out for great talent.
But a High Noble has to recommend you first.
Escaped?
Let him go. No need to chase him.
You're young and accomplished.
Who was your mentor at court?
His Excellency, Inspector Eunuch Gao.
He was devoted to the court.
But Empress Zhang and Li Fuguo smeared his name
and he died in exile.
His Majesty has since eliminated that cabal.
I killed Li Fuguo myself.
You're loyal to your mentor.
That's rare.
It's a pity that back then my family
had no one such as yourself.
Only when I got to Chang'an did I know
people there saw the Gaos
as a clan past its prime.
PRINCE QI'S RESIDENCE, CHANG'AN
LI GUINIAN
Watch it.
S-so sorry, Mr Li.
Prince Qi thinks your spear dance marvellous
and insisted I include it
in tonight's program for Princess Yuzhen.
Personally, I don't see
what's so marvellous.
The way you wield it
is less dancer than warrior.
Mr Li, please, please forgive me.
I will do my best
to earn their applause.
Princess Yuzhen is very cultured.
Good luck.
So be it.
I respect Prince Qi's wishes.
I have to go see that zither player too.
Prince Qi pushed two new acts on me tonight.
Sparkling bright as the stream
Their scents and flowers' aroma blend
Whose boys are those loafing on the banks?
Prince Qi.
PRINCESS YUZHEN
PRINCE QI
Only Prince Qi
PRINCESS YUZHEN
PRINCE QI
truly loved talent.
He said
His Majesty adored his sister Yuzhen
If she recommended someone
he'd appoint them.
That night, Prince Qi held a party
so I could show her my skills.
It's a bit scary.
As a battle technique it's superb.
Spear, spear.
The Gao Spear can kill enemies
but it can't impress a woman.
Defaming the princess behind her back.
- Who...
- How dare you, Gao Shi.
I'm teasing. Looks like I scared you.
You... you naughty kid.
Prince Qi told me about tonight's program.
Your spear skills are impressive.
Such a shame
you lack a battlefield to use them on.
Today you must settle
for courting applause at a little party.
Little Master, how are you related to Prince Qi?
I'm not related.
My humble surname is Du, my name is Fu.
DU FU AS A YOUTH
Du Fu, from Jingzhao.
Ah, the Du family of Jingzhao.
It's an honor.
Come, listen.
This is Prince Qi's other program for tonight.
Who's this?
You've surely heard of him.
He's from the Wang clan of Hedong.
WANG WEI
Wang Wei.
Red beans in the south flourish in the spring.
I knew his poetry and painting were sublime.
but not that he also played so beautifully.
The thing about him
is that he's a bit cold.
I try to talk to him
but he always ignores me.
Such a personality isn't good at
"Passing the Scroll".
So Prince Qi invited him tonight too.
I do like you though.
Gao Shi, what are your other talents?
Princess Yuzhen likes music and dance.
And painting too.
I'm no good at any of that.
But as for poetry...
This way.
So striking and so talented!
What's going on?
This robe suits you better.
Princess Yuzhen is here.
Your Highness.
M'Lord.
I didn't realise you were the famous Wang Wei.
I've wanted to meet you for a long time.
Please, sit with me.
I wouldn't presume.
If you'd like a referral, just say the word.
You have a gift for recognising greatness.
This way.
Actually, I'm so-so at those arts as well.
Especially my calligraphy hideous.
Practice doesn't improve it.
I love writing poetry.
But poetry
anyone can do that.
The successful candidates are "picking flowers".
- Look!
- "Picking flowers"?
It's a custom.
Pass the exams
and you may enter any Chang'an garden
to pick flowers
for tonight's celebrations in Qujiang.
Are you okay?
Pardon me!
That was you with the spear last night.
And it's you!
Thank you, sir.
I'm so sorry. Are you alright?
No problem. Please don't worry.
CHANG JIAN
I'm glad.
Return home a failure, birds and flowers jeer.
Better to remain in Chang'an one more year.
Such a coincidence, dear.
We're off to sing at the Qujiang parties.
We didn't expect to meet you here.
The scholar gave the lady a flower.
She'll have a lucky year.
M-miss!
Last night at Prince Qi's residence
what song were you singing?
The lyrics were beautiful.
I learned it a few days ago.
"Gathering Lotuses"
The lyrics are by a brilliant young man.
Li Bai.
Li Bai?
Miss, we need to hurry
we can't be late for the celebrations.
Li Bai.
His fame had already reached Chang'an.
Even a singsong girl knew his name.
Wang Wei, Li Bai, they were right.
Unknowns had no business in Chang'an.
I needed to go elsewhere,
make a name, then come to Chang'an.
So you went home?
Yes, but before I did,
I had an appointment to keep.
You went to Yangzhou?
I went to Yangzhou.
FORT YUNSHAN OUTSKIRTS
Let's go report this!
YANGZHOU
They were from Daming Temple. You owe me!
Miss!
Yangzhou
was full of temptation and sweetness.
At the inn there, I asked about Li Bai.
Everyone knew him.
Where is he?
Brother Gao!
This is so unexpected!
And so great. I've really missed you!
Brother Li-
we agreed to meet in a year. I kept my word.
We agreed to what?
This fellow, I've told you about him
Dongting Lake, strong as an ox,
felling thieves with one blow.
A Bohai Gao, Gao Shi, Gao Thirty-Five!
You're just in time.
We're about to do something big.
What's that?
We're going to save someone.
Come, come!
From the dragon's pool and tiger's lair
we'll rescue a divine beauty!
Dragon's pool, tiger's lair?
Stop there!
Brother Gao
don't you want to see who you saved?
Master Li
I was at Master Su's banquet.
I was only halfway into my dance
when you barged in and stole me away.
Where are you taking me?
Banquet?
Su Sixteen. Such a bore.
Dancing for such bores is so dull.
I rescued you from all that tedium.
Shouldn't you thank me?
I thank you.
But my mother won't forgive you.
Whatever. We're off to Master Pei's house.
Master Pei is with you?
Pei Twelve's father
General Pei is hosting a banquet tonight.
Wu Daozi is coming to paint.
The General will do a sword dance to inspire him.
Wu Daozi's painting, General Pei's sword-
two treasures of the Tang in one night!
That's what I call a great banquet.
Stop that boat!
She's on that boat! Chase it!
Row faster, faster!
Master Li, don't be angry.
I can't make General Pei's banquet.
That's my bad luck.
What if instead, here on this boat
I show you my new Zhezhi Dance?
Why not.
Great!
Dance! I'll play the drum for you.
Thank you, Master Li.
A beautiful Zhezhi Dance.
A beauty's smile as precious as gold
Rippling her sleeves, she sings an exotic tune.
Master Li, did you like tonight's dance?
It outshone the moon on the river!
Here, this is all the money I have on me.
It's your reward.
Thank you, kind sir.
But
you caused big trouble tonight.
My mother needs comforting too.
Of course, yes!
This ring is white jade from Mt Tian.
Take it!
Thank you so much.
Marvelous dancing, a beautiful night!
Youth is fleeting; age is upon me
Flowers fade; my heart is heavy
I long in dreams; reach for that sun-filled place.
Come!
THE PEI RESIDENCE
Incredible!
I can't see.
We're late, we were delayed on the river.
Let's go to the window.
I've got it!
The Way of calligraphy!
ZHANG XU
I've got it!
- The Way of calligraphy!
- Yes, while watching Wu Daozi paint.
Zhang Xu found the Way?
Come, Brother Gao.
Bravo!
What luck!
Wonderful!
Only in magnificent Yangzhou
do you find such fabulous parties.
The night is young.
In which songhouse
should we continue the fun?
We'll party til the sun lights the east.
Brother Gao, aren't you coming?
Brother Li, forgive my directness.
But spending money like water
how long can you go on like this?
Won't your incredible talent
dissipate amongst such nightly revels?
Gee, uh...
If not amidst Yangzhou's wine and beauties
where should it dissipate?
A great man aims to serve his country.
Serve the country?
Talent alone means you can serve?
Your family's spear is famous.
Would the talented Master Gao
allow a talentless, common wastral like me
to challenge him to a contest?
My pleasure.
Great!
The Pei Sword and the Gao Spear
both arts perfected on the battlefield.
What a good contest.
Yes, but the Gao Spear
wasn't designed for performance
but for killing enemies.
Bravo!
Dancing or fighting with the sword
it's all related. I understand now!
My father's swordsmanship is stellar
and he's a great military man.
But
Imperial Chancellor Li Linfu
only promotes non-Han generals
while restraining the great Han families.
My father
might be the best swordsman ever
but at home in Yangzhou
he can only use his sword to entertain.
Brother Gao
Did you know
that though my family has boys
only I
am the true inheritor of his art?
And yet
I'm a woman.
No door to serving my country is open to me.
A woman's talent!
Talent! Talent!
Pear blossoms drunk on spring's blush
The verdant stream plucks night's strings
Golden times are fleeting
Storms make gloomy the years.
In Yangzhou, everyone knows her.
An exceptional woman
as fine a poet as a swordswoman.
She dresses like a man. Her father indulges her.
Don't fret losing to Pei Twelve
is nothing to be ashamed of.
Let's go, let's get a drink.
Time for a drink.
Brother Li, it's me who lost.
I'm also aware
of my youthful arrogance and over-confidence.
I'm neither learned, nor a great martial artist.
I'll go home, study and practice hard
until the day comes that I'm ready
and on that day I will finally shine!
Brother Li, I take my leave.
But you just got to Yangzhou!
The Great Eagle will soar one day.
Gao Thirty-Five
you just stopped stuttering!
It's true.
I never stuttered again after that.
Reporting!
Sir, it's urgent military news.
The whole Tubo army has left Yunshan.
and is headed towards Lushui Pass.
The whole army?
We saw it ourselves, it's true.
There's cavalry and infantry.
Altogether 70 or 80 thousand.
How far are they from Lushui Pass?
Twenty li, about six hours.
Six hours.
Please, sit. We still have time.
LIANG GARDENS
I returned to Liang Gardens in Shangqiu.
Our family estate still had some fields
and several old houses.
Three years soon passed.
It was spring again.
Green woods fringe the village;
verdant mountains surround it.
Brother Gao
why can other people study alone
but I have to read something first
for you to remember it?
Gao Shi
we caught a thief by the village temple.
He says he's your friend!
Brother Gao, long time no see.
Li Bai!
It's true, he's an old friend.
Please, let him go.
He was napping naked in the temple!
He doesn't look respectable.
I apologise.
This friend from afar
is rather casual by nature.
- Mr Gao says he's a friend.
- Leave them.
Brother Li, how'd you get here?
Gao Shi
remember I taught you the art of wrestling?
To answer force with feints?
Come, let's have a match.
Gao Shi, you've improved a lot.
You win, Brother Gao.
You look well.
Brother Li, have you been well?
No, I've been wretched.
A few months ago I got very sick
and almost died in Yangzhou.
Forget it!
Come, let's drink. C'mon.
Sure.
Happily, I just caught some fish.
They'll go well with wine.
Fishing with straight hooks like Duke Jiang?
He never caught any fish.
But I have.
Cheers.
I'm working hard on my martial skills.
Oh, I'm learning to write poetry too.
I know.
Lonely view of autumn grasses
Bitter winds blow for thousands of miles
You've read my poetry?
People are reading it everywhere.
Brother Gao, your splendid talent
has finally burst forth!
I speak easily now
But studying is still hard for me.
A village student has to read to me
before I can absorb anything.
That's fine. Who cares?
As a boy studying at Elephant Ear Mountain
I never seemed to improve.
One day I skipped class.
Know what I saw by the stream?
An old woman, polishing a rod
of metal this thick.
I asked, what are you doing?
The old woman said
"Effort plus time turns a rod into a needle fine."
So I went back and studied.
Studying is always hard.
You see, I had to work hard too.
Brother Li, is that a true story?
If I tell it of course it's true.
Brother Gao, are you still single?
Poor as I am
and with no hope of an official position,
what family would give me their daughter's hand?
I'm getting married.
Congratulations! What family is she from?
The Xus of Anlu.
Retired Chancellor Xu?
That's right.
I really must congratulate you!
These are the celebrated Liang Gardens?
A thousand years have passed.
Now all that's left is this collapsed wall
and a few ruined pavilions.
Worldly prosperity is an illusion.
Ephemeral as a flower's bloom.
All those years in Yangzhou
passed as though in a dream.
That day when we said goodbye
I received terrible news from home.
My father suffered a sudden illness
and passed away in his prime.
Of all the people in the world
he loved me best.
Before I got home, my brothers split the estate.
They said I'd already frittered away my share.
I didn't get a cent.
Overnight
I found myself
an outcast, persona non grata.
I...
I had no idea.
Thrown out of home
I set myself up in a little inn
where I fell suddenly and terribly ill
and nearly died.
That night...
Moonlight at the foot of my bed
Appears to me like frost.
Lifting my head, I behold the moon
Lowering it,
I think of home.
I know that poem of yours.
What I was saying
is that I'm done with my prodigal ways.
I'm getting married!
In a month, I'll go to Anlu
and pay my respects to the Xus.
They have a courtyard where I can live.
I want to have children.
Though my sons won't bear my surname
the surname Xu
is that of a great and respected family.
You're joining your bride's family?
He said the Xus were a powerful family.
By joining them as a son-in-law
he could change his status
He was the son of a lowly merchant.
For his children to be surnamed Xu
was a good thing.
But I was totally opposed to it.
Taking her family name?
Society disdained men who did that
In the future how could he face
his own ancestors?
It's not far from Xiangyang. Look!
He asked me to go with him to Xiangyang
to get some advice.
If his most respected and trusted friend
was also against it
then he'd give up the plan.
Meng Haoran lives in a wonderland.
Brother Gao, you'll adore Meng Haoran!
Meng Haoran.
Of course I knew his name.
Deep sleeps of spring
all around me birds sing.
A loud stormy night
countless petals fall.
MENG RESIDENCE
Master Meng isn't home. He left two days ago.
He left?
My Master said
to tell friends he'd gone to Jiangxia,
where he'd change boats for Yangzhou.
I have to catch up with him.
Brother Li!
Hurry, we'll race to Jiangxia
and catch him before his boat leaves.
This business with the Xus
I wrote to him about it.
I'm sure he's going to Yangzhou to see me!
And so we returned to Jiangxia
and Yellow Crane Tower.
Which is the boat for Yangzhou?
The boat to Yangzhou
just set sail.
Brother Li!
Mr Meng!
The advice I asked for
should I do it or not?
The sound of the wind muffled his answer.
Mr Meng!
Brother Gao, I need your strength!
YES OR NO
YES
Waiter!
Give me brush and ink.
I want to write a poem!
Okay, sir, let me go.
The lone boat slowly vanishes against the sky
I see only the Yangtze flowing
to the edge of the world.
Waiter
these excellent lines of mine.
How do they compare with Cui Hao's?
Very fine, very fine.
It's just that, it's a bit short.
Only four lines.
Master Cui's poem is eight lines.
What's length have to do with quality?
Brother Gao
I was just overcome with inspiration.
NO
After parting that day
more years fled past.
I decided to join the army.
I'm awkward in company.
I didn't have Li Bai's ease
or his and Wang Wei's immense talent.
We Gaos have always been military men.
It's in braving danger we make our name.
That's the Gao family's destiny.
JIZHOU, NORTH OF THE GREAT WALL
You're known for your literary talent.
Why not stay and be a military secretary
ZHANG SHOUGUI
instead of leaving to lead a tiny cavalry?
General-
The districts of Andong
were where my grandfather fought 30 years ago.
Not to follow his example would bring dishonor.
I must put on my armor and do battle.
Come.
This man leads a frontline cavalry.
If you win, I'll give you your own cavalry.
Okay.
What are we competing in?
Wrestling.
Good choice!
Our opponents are Khitans.
They're renowned wrestlers.
Fine. Let's wrestle.
Bravo!
Well done!
You're a worthy heir to the Gaos.
AUTHORISED
TANG
Captain Gao!
That whole year in Jizhou
I didn't write a single poem.
The Khitan army is on the move!
I was ordered to locate the Khitans.
For months
we found no trace of them.
There! Over there!
The Khitans are burning the plains!
Retreat!
Orders from the General：
A cavalry platoon of the Right Army
twelve li to the northwest
has been ambushed by a river.
We need to relieve the siege now!
All soldiers mobilize!
From start to finish
we never found the Khitans' main forces.
The next order I received
was to retreat and hold our position.
A retreat
- Dismount!
- is far more dangerous
than an advance.
Beautiful!
Gao Thirty-five
The Jizhou army
isn't a place for you.
Go home.
PUJINYI INN
Those soldiers are off to Longxi.
Their hair is whiter than mine
and they still can't shed their armor.
Is that the inn's poetry pavilion?
Wherever they're from, poets
like to leave a little something here.
Want to write a poem?
There's charcoal by the wall.
I...
wrote poetry again.
O'er the northeast rises the smoke
and dust of battle
The Han fight the fierce enemy far from home
The men vanquish all before them.
Gao Shi.
Hey.
Gao Thirty-five.
Gao Shi.
Who's there?
Me!
Brother Li?
Brother Li! What are you doing here?
Brother Gao, ah, Brother Gao
I never imagined meeting you here.
I just saw on that poetry board
quite by accident the poem you wrote.
I asked and it's true, you're here!
Brother Li, you...
why are you dressed like that?
I'm fleeing for my life.
That new poem of yours-
Gao Shi
it's the best one you've ever written.
Congratulations!
While in cruel battle soldiers die
In the general's tent, beauties dance
Young wives down south weep, comfortless
The men marching north gaze back at emptiness
Gao Thirty-five
these lines will live forever!
Brother Li, you're too kind.
Brother Li, why are you on the run?
It's a long story.
Years ago, after we parted at Yellow Crane Tower
I went to Anlu.
Later my father-in-law died.
He'd raised a younger relative
as his heir.
He pushed me aside.
Didn't you warn me
not to join my wife's family?
One day Master Danqiu came by.
He'd entered a Taoist order.
He's an old friend from home.
Have you heard of him?
Of course.
A Great Eagle can't fit in a finch's nest!
So I left Anlu
and travelled with Master Danqiu
seeking the Way to immortality.
MASTER DANQIU
It's not something that comes quickly.
A friend in the Youzhou Army
invited me to visit.
Maybe
I could serve the Tang on the frontier.
As a result,
guess what I discovered?
An Lushan
was planning a rebellion.
Governor An Lushan
is the Tang's most trusted general on the borders.
That's a capital crime!
Do you have proof?
Yes.
That day I went to a tailor
to pick up my robe.
This one.
The tailor made a mistake.
He gave me the wrong robe-
an official one.
But not one of the Tang!
I didn't think much about it at the time.
I returned the robe.
But as it turned out
I went for a stroll that afternoon
and passing the tailor's on my way back
saw that his shop
was in flames. Nothing was left.
I was deciding what to do
when my friend rushed over
and warned me not to go home
but to flee immediately.
The tailor and his apprentices
were arrested by the governor's personal guards
and executed.
As I left the city, the gates shut.
and the whole way here
I noticed
soldiers on my tail.
I need to report to the court.
I'm sure
that official robe
was part of the rebel An Lushan's plans
to form his own court!
This is a very grave matter.
But the court won't believe
the words of a commoner.
I have to find an official
who'll speak to the Court for me.
and report the situation.
Everyone who tries, dies.
It's damn useless.
Who's there?
An Lushan's ambitions
are well known in the borderlands.
But Li Linfu needs An Lushan and Shi Siming
as allies in court.
As for the emperor
he's getting old
and doesn't like trouble.
So what's the point of reporting?
Please, who are you?
You
Li Bai, Gao Shi-
I've heard of you both.
You're poets.
You've heard of me?
Quick, down!
They found me!
But if everyone knows about it
why do they still want to kill me?
That official robe
maybe they're not ready
for people to find out.
Li Bai, come out.
If you don't
we'll burn the place down.
Li Bai, those poems of yours
I like them.
You out there
An Lushan's men, right?
Who are you?
I'm Guo Ziyi.
GUO ZIYI
Serving general under Geshu Han,
Govenor of Longyou.
GUO ZIYI
Guo Ziyi?
Surprised to see you here.
You're meddling in the Pinglu Army's affairs now?
Yes.
I have a houseful of men here
who thanks to your noise
can't get a good night's sleep.
So it's all of our business.
Guo Ziyi, your great reputation
precedes you. Great skills.
Since you want to deal with this
the Longyou army will owe us one.
You'll pay for this one day.
Let's go.
So, before the sun sets
they're going to execute you at the inn?
The empire is in trouble.
The country needs men like you
brave and strategic.
How can it be that
a fire breaks out in a military camp
and you get blamed and beheaded!
Military discipline is harsh.
I've executed others in the past
today it's my turn.
Heaven decrees it.
But it's wrong!
Heaven gave us these gifts
surely our day will come!
When I arrived yesterday
I heard Geshu Han was leading his army west.
They're half a day's march away.
Sir Geshu is an old friend of my family.
I'll go plead with him.
Do all you can to protect Brother Guo.
I'll be back before sunset!
Hurry.
Move!
Stop the execution!
So the two of you
together saved Guo Ziyi's life.
Such a talented man
shouldn't die a wrongful death.
Who could've guessed
that later, he'd suppress An Lushan's rebellion
and restore the Tang?
No one could've known.
Brother Gao,
How'd you persuade Geshu Han?
It wasn't too hard.
He wanted me to work for him.
I said that in the future
wherever he led his troops into battle
he just had to call for me
and I'd serve him as secretary.
But you never wanted
a desk job, right?
I still don't.
I give myself ten years.
Ten years.
Gao Shi, the first time we met
was ten years ago, yes?
Yes.
Ten years.
Right.
I'll also give myself ten years.
Let's see if in ten years
we can make it into the court.
I take my leave
Gao Shi-
Hard is the journey, hard is the journey
So many forks in the road, which is the true one?
One day the wind and waves will favor me
I'll raise white sails and head to sea.
Gao Thirty-Five
you're back!
Still want me to read to you?
Have you made progress?
Not really, I still need you!
Great!
LIANG GARDENS
Liang Gardens were even more of a ruins.
I never imagined that the poem I wrote at Pujinyi Inn
in a rush of indignation
would spread wide and far.
From then on everyone knew
that I, Gao Shi, was a poet.
What's more, after years of effort
I could finally study on my own.
But, the poem's fame
made the general I spoke of
the one with the dancing girls furious.
And caused all the high officials
to avoid me like the plague.
What they wanted
were people to flatter them.
Not a literary man
who could ruin their reputation.
A literary man.
Back home in Shangqiu,
ten years slipped past.
Gao Thirty-Five
I hope you've been well...
Li Bai wrote to me.
In ten years searching for immortality and the Tao
he found neither.
His fame, however, had grown.
Out of the blue came an imperial summons
and he was called to Chang'an.
As a member of the Hanlin Academy
he won the emperor's admiration.
His Majesty Xuanzong believed in the Tao.
Li Bai said
the one who recommended him to the court
was Princess Yuzhen.
Oh?
Who'd imagine
Princess Yuzhen would recommend Li Bai!
By then she had converted to Taoism.
She adored Taoists, unworldly people.
Unworldly people.
He
finally found the shortcut to the court.
He invited me to Chang'an.
He said he had many friends there.
In court and beyond, everyone loved him.
He wanted to help me make my mark.
Hurry, come to Chang'an, don't delay!
CHANG'AN
Excuse me, sir
how can I get to Longevity Hall?
Mr Li is truly an unbridled genius.
I toss back my head, laugh at the sky;
we will not stay down for long.
Beautiful line. Peerless!
How about
Ziyang the Immortal, asks me to play my jade flute
Such a free spirit!
Excuse me
is this Li Bai's home?
Yes, he lives here.
Are you a fan, too?
Every day, his fans come
to gather here.
It's quite a scene.
Gao Thirty-Five?
It's been ages, ages!
And you, my good man, are...?
Twenty years ago, at Prince Qi's residence
we hid together inside a lion.
I'm Du Fu!
DU FU
So it's you!
This is wonderful.
I've been reading your poems in recent years.
Everyone loves your border poem
But my favourite is your line
Fresh breezes blow for thousands of miles;
a traveler sails home on the river.
So free and elegant!
You're too kind.
Your
One must ascend the highest peak
to see how small the mountains are
expresses such lofty ideals.
Are you here to see Li Bai too?
Yes. I knocked but no one answered.
He hasn't been home for days.
He's quite a drinker!
He'll be at the Qujiang wineshop
where exotic beauties
perform new songs and dances.
Come, let's go.
We'll look for him together.
Qujiang Pool!
The year's scholar parties are over
but the wine shops
still do a roaring trade.
Brother Du, are you preparing for the exams?
I've tested twice
but didn't make it.
My own Qujiang party
will have to wait.
Here we are.
Over there!
Inspector He!
Inspector He is fine.
See? Sound asleep in the pool!
HE ZHIZHANG
Hurry, Li Bai is up there now!
What was Inspector He's line?
ZHANG XU
Don't mourn spring's fallen petals
spring's fallen petals
Great line!
Not an easy one to follow!
C'mon, if you don't do well
you have to stay on the plank!
Tomorrow we enter a glorious garden!
How's that?
It'll do. You can get down.
You need to do some calligraphy.
No problem.
Du Fu!
- A new friend?
- It's Cui Zongzhi's turn.
Can't I pass?
- Zongzhi, up you go.
- No!
I'm afraid of heights!
CUI ZONGZHI
You're younger than Inspector He
you need a longer plank!
Don't be afraid.
Here's a lute.
- Play and you'll be fine!
- Two lines!
Li Bai.
You missed! You're fined two cups!
Gao Shi, Gao Thirty-Five!
Come, come. This is
Gao Shi-
you've all heard of him, right?
We've been good friends for over 20 years.
Come, let me introduce you.
Prince of Ruyang!
Emperor Ruizong's eldest grandson!
We're all equals here, even the imperial clan!
It's an honor.
And this here
is Li Yong, Prefect Li-
best "running script" calligrapher of our day.
- A pleasure!
- I'm honored.
And these two gentlemen
are Wang Changling and Cen Shen!
You've heard of them, of course.
The bright moon of Qin, the passes of Han
The soldiers on the march have yet to return.
Just a minor poem.
As if brought by a spring breeze
Snow blooms on trees like pear blossoms
An honor.
You're all known for your border poems.
Honoured to meet you.
Cui Zongzhi young and gifted!
I'm honored.
Zongzhi's lute playing
expresses the anxiety of the battle march.
Brother Wang Wei!
Brother Wang Wei is here too.
Such serendipity!
Brother Wang Wei
join our poetry game?
Enjoy yourselves, I have to be somewhere.
That burp cost Wang Wei
ten years of self-cultivation.
My turn!
I'll have a go.
Gao Thirty-five, Gao Thirty-five
quickly, tell me-
what brings you here to Chang'an?
Why didn't you drop me a line first?
I...
I received your urgent letter.
My urgent letter?
Brother Changling, are you having trouble?
Brother Changling
if you can't continue the poem
you'll have to pay the penalty.
Here I come!
Give me the lute.
Li Bai is no ordinary mortal.
He's a celestial being!
So when can I get back to the heavens?
Exotic Beauty dance faster!
Here we go!
A zither from Dragon Gate's parasol tree
A jade cup with wine of perfect clarity
Bravo!
- Bravo!
- Li Bai a merchant's son
with exotic bloodlines.
And yet so famous.
The Tang really embraces all kinds.
I tune the strings and drink with thee
Lovely as flowers, Exotic Beauty
Selling wine, smiling at spring breezes
Smiling at spring breezes, dancing robes aflutter
You didn't follow the last verse
you wrote a new poem.
It's not even the same form.
Penalty!
Sure, what's the penalty?
Write ten poems or you can't come down.
Ten poems is nothing.
I'll write one hundred for you!
Beauty dance faster still!
Brother Gao!
Even my horse is keen to go home.
Brother Du
I take my leave.
No need to see me off.
You only just got to Chang'an
and now you're rushing off?
Why not stay a few more days?
Li Bai
when Brother Li Bai sobers up
he'll definitely want to keep you here.
This endless drinking
when will he ever sober up?
The Great Eagle soars amongst the clouds.
He has no time for mundanities.
I don't blame him.
Brother Du
before I leave
would you go somewhere with me?
QIAN TOMBS
Brother Du
did you know
that when my grandfather
was 20, as a cavalry officer
he captured the Turks' Chebi Khan.
At 30, he helped Li Ji
annihilate the Goguryeo Kingdom.
At 40, he smashed the Silla.
At 42
he passed away.
I'm 43 this year.
Brother Du
I hope you pass the exam and are admitted to court.
Here's to your early success.
Farewell!
Take care.
As for me
I returned home once more.
LIANG GARDENS ONE YEAR LATER
Good shot.
Why didn't you shoot?
A solitary goose
flying back south
let it go.
Brother Gao, such compassion
are you planning to become a Buddhist?
Brother Du Fu!
Brother Gao!
Have you been well?
Gao Thirty-five.
Li Bai
you...
why are you wearing Taoist robes?
These last few years in Chang'an
Li Linfu became increasingly
jealous and ill-willed towards Li Bai.
The emperor's Precious Consort hates me.
I thought I'd written a poem
in praise of her beauty.
I never imagined
she'd think I was mocking her.
so her cousin,
Chancellor Yang Guozhong, hates him too.
Chang'an
has become a treacherous place.
His Majesty...
I didn't win the Emperor's favor
and fell rudely from grace.
To bow and scrape before the high-born
Steals all the joy from my heart.
So... what do you plan to do?
I will enter a Taoist order.
A Taoist order?
Gao Shi-
I'm not joking.
Really.
Behold these ruins
once King Liang's garden palace.
Where is he now?
This terrace
once rang with song and dance.
When we met in our youth
we both had such ambition.
But in the blink of an eye
here we are, nearly fifty.
My wife
passed away recently.
The ways of this world
are no longer for me.
Gao Shi-
Life is short.
I want to become a Taoist hermit.
Master Gao of Beihai
has prepared a Taoist altar in Jinan
He'll officially ordain Brother Li there.
Brother Gao, you may not know
but ordination is an arduous undertaking.
Brother Li must ascend that altar
and chant scripture and spells
day and night.
So I want to ask the two of you
to support me.
Gao Shi-
you're my best friend.
You understand me.
With my character
if I go alone
I'll never make it.
This Great Eagle
can no longer fly
and doesn't want to either.
He said
I was his best friend.
Was I?
In any case
I agreed.
TAOIST ALTAR IN JINAN
Newly ordained Taoists,
Brother Li-
- Brother Li -
- the rituals have concluded.
Nothingness will be your teacher
and nature your friend.
Refine your snowy countenance
and extend your golden life.
Brother Gao
I saw the immortals of heaven
inviting me to return there
I want to return to heaven
Let's congratulate Brother Li Bai
CEN XUN MASTER DANQIU
on his admission to the Taoist orders.
LI YONG
Brother Li
you're a Taoist now.
You're a holy man.
Are you still going to drink like this?
Yes!
Wine is part of my spiritual practice.
It's the nectar of immortality.
Gao Shi-
in the 20 years of our acquaintance
this is the first time I've seen you
drink with such gusto!
Come! Come!
Drink up!
Bottoms up!
I can't drink anymore.
That won't do.
I'm done too.
No way.
Master Cen
Master Danqiu
You have to keep drinking!
Everyone has to drink.
No one stop!
I have a poem!
I'll revive your spirits with poetry.
Can you see
the Yellow River decanting from the sky
And racing to the sea never to return?
Can you see the grief of white hair in the mirrors
As dawn's black silk turns to evening snow?
When life goes well, be joyous
Never show the moon an empty cup
Heaven gave me talent for a reason
Spend now, riches return in season
Stew the lamb, prepare the ox, let us feast
Tonight we'll drink three hundred cups at least
Master Cen, Master Danqiu
drink and don't put down your cups
I'll sing for you
Please lend your ears
Bells and jades are not so precious
As eternal inebriation
Ancient sages leave no name
It's great drinkers who enjoy great fame
At the table of Prince Chen of old
Wine flowed like water
Hosts shouldn't fret over costs
Buy more wine and fill those cups
Fine horses, expensive robes
Tell the servant to sell these for wine
We'll banish sorrow from this world
We'll banish
sorrow from this world.
Li Bai-
I have to go.
You're going?
Yes.
After this goodbye
who knows when we'll meet again?
Perhaps we won't see each other again.
If we don't
see you in the celestial realms.
You're a celestial being, returning home.
As for me
I'm of this world.
I'll linger here.
Li Bai-
I'm off to the frontier to serve under Geshu Han.
I'll keep my ten year vow.
What... what vow?
Your poem said it all.
The Yellow River racing to the sea,
never to return.
Though I'm running out of time
when I face my ancestors
I'll be able to tell them
although I couldn't be like them
blooded heroes on the battlefield
and I was only able to become
a very minor clerk
yet with each stroke of my brush
I too galloped across battlefields.
Galloped...
Such lofty spirit!
Bravo, bravo!
But, Gao Shi-
If you're going to the frontier at your age
let me test how strong you are!
Come
let's wrestle.
Sure!
Gao Shi-
you won.
Go then.
Farewell.
Warriors of Zhao with tassels flying
Curved swords bright as shining snow
Silver saddles on white steeds
Galloping past like shooting stars
I wrote this poem 20 years ago
it was my impression of you, Gao Shi!
The living are but passers-by
The dead have gone back home
The world is an inn that welcomes and farewells
The ancient dust is soaked with tears.
LONGYOU MILITARY CAMP
LONGYOU REGION GOVERNOR, GESHU HAN
When I first got to Longyou
we laid siege to Stone Fort.
STONE FORT
It's easy to defend, hard to attack.
For six months, 30,000 Tang soldiers laid siege.
Casualties were heavy.
Starved of supplies, the Tubos finally surrendered.
That's when we learned
only 600 men had defended the fort.
A mere 600 defenders
kept us pacing outside its walls half a year.
Yunshan Fort
is another Stone Fort.
Reporting!
Dawn.
I'm not here about Stone Fort.
Return to the topic of Li Bai.
Although I was at the frontier
I often read his new poems.
He roamed the great mountains and rivers.
He had regrets, but his poetry
became even more brilliant.
Sir
Do you have many regrets in life?
Regrets?
Of course.
Even if I perform meritorious deeds
only in the biographies of eunuchs
will people ever see my name.
The situation in the country is worrying.
The court is in chaos.
Everyone feels in danger.
Among the poets I know
Wang Changling and Cui Zongzhi are in exile.
Governor of Beihai, Li Yong.
was 70 when they beat him to death.
Frontier life is hard, but uncomplicated.
Ten years flew by.
My life was nearing its end.
These ten years seemed uneventful.
In all this time
I only saw Li Bai once.
I was in Xuan City on official business.
It was at the ferry crossing.
Who's that?
Li Bai, the great poet
and Taoist too!
Magistrate Wang Lun is a big fan.
that's Li Bai's new wife.
The granddaughter of Chancellor Zong.
LADY ZONG, LI BAI'S WIFE
MAGISTRATE WANG LUN
Things have worked out for him.
He joined her family, not the other way round.
For such an eminent family, I'd do it too.
And so would you!
Li Bai, ah, Li Bai-
I thought the paths we were on
were fixed.
But sometimes, suddenly,
within the space of a day,
a few centuries worth of events occur.
An Lushan
had been plotting rebellion for over ten years.
Who'd have thought that
Li Linfu, that rotten old stick
would be the last pillar to fall, toppling the house
Although Li Linfu was avaricious
he was also brilliant and capable.
After 19 years of holding the dynasty together
he died suddenly.
Yang Guozhong took his place.
An Lushan
rebelled.
Reporting!
Pass on the order
to gather the troops.
Official Appointments： Secretary,
Ranks Eight and below
TONG PASS
Gao Xianzhi and Feng Changqing
were both executed.
The great dynasty has no generals left.
I'm the last, and I'm half-paralysed.
If I defy orders to fight this important battle
the court will naturally execute me too.
Who will succeed me?
I fear it'll be the Eunuch Inspector Bian Lingcheng.
If I were a little younger
it'd be much better.
Ursa Major sits high in the sky
Geshu is armed day and night
The Tubos lurk about the herds
But dare not cross Lintao
Ride out the pass.
Open the gates!
The whole army is in agreement.
The Tang's luck has run out.
The world belongs to An Lushan's Yan dynasty.
We're defecting to An Lushan.
Geshu Han.
We'll ask you one last time
will you surrender
or not?
Help me onto my horse.
Sadly, I spent a life practicing the spear
yet never used it on a battlefield
But I'll use it against these backstabbers.
Gao Shi-
It's me those traitors are after.
If you can, I want you to escape the siege
and tell the emperor
that not all northern tribes are traitors!
General!
Go, Gao Shi!
I, Geshu Han,
won't surrender!
Go!
CHANG'AN
Tong Pass had fallen.
The court had fled from Chang'an.
I chased westwards after them.
They killed the Chancellor
and made the Precious Consort commit suicide.
I heard many officials and soldiers
had surrendered to An Lushan.
Among those who hadn't
some powerful and ambitious men
had mutinied.
The world was in chaos.
Early summer,
the 44th year of Emperor Xuanzong's reign.
Emperor Xuanzong fled Chang'an for Sichuan.
Mid-summer, in Ningxia,
his son was crowned Emperor Suzong.
Xuanzong was named Emperor Emeritus.
Xuanzong appointed his sons
to the posts of regional governors.
He made Prince Yong Governor
of the Four Regions and General of Jiangling.
In autumn,
Suzong ordered Prince Yong back to Sichuan.
Prince Yong refused.
YANGZHOU.
SIX MONTHS AFTER THE FALL OF TONG PASS.
The new Southern Region Governor
has control of the Yangtze-Huai area
and quelled the prince's rebellion.
GAO SHI,
SOUTHERN REGION GOVERNOR
Reporting, sir.
Rebel troops are gathering at Jiangling.
Sir
Prince Yong orders state
revenues sent to Jiangling.
Cavalry scouts have left Jiangling.
Reporting, sir
Prince Yong's troops have left Jiangling,
whereabouts uncertain.
Prince Yong issued a call to all "heroes".
Read it.
It's said that extraordinary crises
give rise to extraordinary people
who achieve extraordinary things. Prince Yong-
It was an extraordinary crisis indeed
that led me, a lowly official of below 8th Rank
within six months
to become the Governor of three regions.
Governor, we have news of Prince Yong's army.
Tell me.
They're coming down the Yangtze
heading for our army in Yangzhou.
They'll arrive in three days.
Prince Yong is a mediocrity,
more ambitious than wise.
If he wanted to win control
he'd ride north to retake Chang'an from the rebels
or east to relieve the siege of Suiyang
It wouldn't be easy, but if successful,
it would change the world.
To ride southeast to attack me
is the cowardly act of a weak ruler.
How can he win the loyalty of heroes?
Does he have much clout?
Have any great men joined in his cause?
Prince Yong has sent out the call
but no one has answered.
Oh, right, except one poet.
Li Bai.
Li Bai?
Li Bai is on Prince Yong's side?
Li Bai wrote eleven whole poems for him.
Eleven poems?
In spring Prince Yong leads his army east
Flying the Imperial standard
His warships calm the winds and sea
Turning mighty rivers into gentle ponds
Mt Beigu was once a fortress of Wu
The towers' reflections shimmered on the water
Madam Li
Prince Yong has been executed.
Li Bai's crime
is that of treason.
LADY ZONG, LI BAI'S WIFE
I know.
Li Bai-
You'd already taken a Taoist path.
Why tangle with worldly affairs?
I failed to advance my spiritual state.
Between mountain and sea, where do immortals dwell?
My wife and I lived a solitary life on Mt Lu.
Prince Yong sent several emissaries
to invite me to help him.
I wanted such a chance my whole life.
Though I'm old, how could I refuse?
You didn't know he was rebelling?
Rebelling?
Wasn't he the Tang's top military officer?
Top military officer?
You didn't realise that in such chaos
all types of men would claim the throne?
But...
Li Bai
do you know where you are now?
Jiangxia.
Yellow Crane Tower.
Yellow Crane Tower?
Right. Gao Shi, Governor Gao
we got to know each other here.
Jiangxia... Yellow Crane Tower...
Gao Thirty-Five will save me.
You...
The depth of your old friendship
means they suspect a cover up!
Don't you see?
I won't say any more.
Just come and see this!
The governor said to tell you
to take a good look.
The world of the Tang
is in turmoil,
devastation as far as the eye can see.
Everywhere is like Jiangxia.
Everywhere is in ruins like Yellow Crane Tower.
Madam Li
Please don't worry about me.
I'm not like my husband
I..
am so disheartened.
I'll spend my remaining years
in seclusion on Mt Lu.
Take care.
Wife!
I'll return to Mt Lu!
Wait for me!
You didn't save Li Bai.
Court politics were like skating on thin ice.
You were always one step from the abyss.
Guo Ziyi interceded with the emperor
and saved him.
Instead of execution, exile in the southwest.
Today the Tang has two elite armies.
One is under Guo Ziyi.
The other
is under your command.
Yes.
The Tubos have besieged Chang'an for three months.
You haven't mobilised your troops.
Are you afraid of repeating Geshu Han's mistake
when his army was annihilated outside Tong Pass?
I'm also afraid of repeating Li Bai's mistake.
In old age, haste leads to error.
But the gossip in court has it
that you and Guo Ziyi
fell out over whether to save Li Bai.
That it's because of this discord
that you won't mobilise your army.
The emperor sent me here
to get to the bottom of all this!
The Tubos have also heard this rumour.
Reporting!
Reporting, Governor
Tubo troops are halfway through the valley.
They're three hours away from here.
Of the men at the Qujiang wineshop that day
He Zhizhang, Wang Changling, Cui Zongzhi are dead.
Though still alive
Du Fu wanders homeless
and Wang Wei, imprisoned by the traitors,
lingers on in desolation.
This candle
whatever happens,
will be extinguished.
The drops of blood on this bandage
are just red wine dregs.
Why are you toying with me?
I apologise, sir.
But it's time to take back Yunshan Fort.
Hand me my spear!
This is a long-forgotten old road.
The steep path can't accomodate a large army.
But it's a shortcut.
In two hours
we'll reach the walls of Yunshan.
FORT YUNSHAN OUTSKIRTS
I understand.
Today, here,
you face the same predicament
as Geshu Han did at Tong Pass.
Whether you stay or go, you lose.
So you're doing neither.
Instead, you're taking a step back
to lure the Tubos into the narrow gorge
recovering Yunshan while cutting off their retreat.
Now those 70,000 Tubo soldiers
have no escape route.
They're like a turtle in an urn.
The Tubos besieging Chang'an
will abandon the siege
to save this turtle.
Brilliant.
But Governor Gao, Lushui Pass may be risky.
It's only held by 6,000 soldiers.
What if they can't defend it?
The Tubo Army
The Tubo Army is coming!
You're right.
But Yan Wu
should be at Lushui Pass by now.
The man who came here was his messenger.
Yan Wu and his 20,000 elite troops
weren't really coming in two days
The reinforcements are here!
but
today at dawn.
My respect.
Your Excellency is famous for
being straightforward
and yet you pulled off this masterful ruse.
Chang'an will be saved.
As Inspector Gao's top disciple
you're of course a great martial artist too.
That year of the rebellion
Inspector Gao took on the enemy single-handed.
And you are his worthy successor!
Governor Gao-
wouldn't such a provocation be too obvious?
There's trouble!
Assemble! Hurry!
This is for Chang'an!
Chang'an!
Fall into formation!
Gao Shi-Do you know how to trick your opponent?
Create a detailed scenario so plausible
that no matter how you view it
it looks real.
So real you even fool yourself.
Yan Wu is young, vigorous and brave.
These 70,000 Tubos
are hungry, cold and will be easily beaten.
Governor Gao knows of course
that this plan
means Yan Wu will get all credit for the victory.
I take my leave.
Governor Gao, when I passed by Chengdu
I saw Du Fu.
Oh, how is he?
Very good.
He said
to thank Your Excellency
for looking after him there.
Du Fu also said
that when Guo Ziyi acted to save Li Bai
it was because Your Excellency had written
to plead with him.
You wanted to save Li Bai
but wanted Guo Ziyi to do it
to prevent talk that you did it out of friendship
which would hurt Li Bai.
Your Excellency, I guessed right, yes?
I also have news of Li Bai.
What?
Before the New Year,
the emperor announced an amnesty.
Li Bai has been pardoned!
He wrote a new poem after his pardon.
I've memorised it.
Out from Baidi amongst the coloured clouds
A thousand miles to Jiangling in a day
The monkeys chitter on the banks
My little boat passes by ten thousand peaks.
Your Excellency, you can tell from the poem
that he's in good spirits.
He hadn't reached his place of exile
when, in Baidi, he got news of his pardon.
Sir, we're ready to depart.
Okay.
In this collection,
whose poems do you like?
Of course, yours.
Cut the sweet talk.
Who else?
Cui Hao, Meng Haoran,
Wang Changling are all great!
Cen Shen too.
Wang Wei his poems
are too hard for me to understand.
You'll understand them one day.
Of course.
Sir, don't think badly of me
but I like Li Bai's poems best.
Chang'an in a flood of moonlight;
ten thousand homely sounds
So great.
By the way, sir
why weren't Du Fu's poems
included in this collection?
Aren't they good enough?
They'll appear in other anthologies.
No taste!
But all the Yellow Crane Tower poems
are in the collection.
Such a pity
the tower was burnt and is no more.
It's okay.
So long as the Yellow Crane Tower poems exist
Yellow Crane Tower is still with us.
Of the three hundred thousand;
only I returned to Chang'an.
Who's is that?
Wang Changling.
A young soldier of Chang'an
mounts the ramparts to regard the Warrior Star
Wang Wei!
At twenty, master of book and sword;
I go to Chang'an
Little devil, I wrote that!
Gazing from afar toward Chang'an;
how I miss its people.
Li Bai! Li Taibai!
Chang'an is like a dream; when might I return?
That's Li Bai too!
Chang'an
so long as poetry exists
and books exist,
Chang'an will still be with us.
Li Bai, at your service.
Gao Shi, at yours.
In winter, Li Bai passed away.
In the second year of Emperor Daizong's reign,
Yan Wu defeated the
70,000 Tubo soldiers trapped in the gorge.
Guo Ziyi recovered Chang'an.
Gao Shi returned to Chang'an
and was demoted.
But he was soon promoted to
Imperial Advisor and made Marquis of Bohai.
Of all the Tang poets,
he had the most distinguished record of service.
Two years later, Gao Shi died.
Chang An
Gazing from Chang'an at brocaded peaks
Doors fling open at the
mountaintop retreat. (Du Mu)
Life is short, drink till you're old
and snow blankets the streets
of Chang'an. (Shu Dan)
Before Calyx Hall the dew is fresh
The people of Chang'an are at peace. (Zhang Yue)
Time loosens beauty's hold
Have you not seen our visitor
Each time he's here, he grows old. (Bai Juyi)
Chang'an in a flood of moonlight
Ten thousand homely sounds (Li Bai)
A young soldier of Chang'an
mounts the ramparts to
regard the Warrior Star (Wang Wei)
I was banished to far-off Changsha
My gaze strains westward towards Chang'an and home
I play my melancholy flute
in the Yellow Crane tower
In spring plum blossoms rain down
on River Town (Li Bai)
As the sun and I set down the mountain
Am I followed by the moon?
Searching for the paths that led here
Green mountain forests so quiet and deep
Long blue mountain mists
Hard is the journey under the blue skies of Shu
In endless mountains I lose my way
Though laugh you may,
I'm still drunk when from dreams I wake
My solitary boat has sailed a thousand streams
With talent I have been endowed
Let stars gamble with the moon and sun
Who thinks of ancient sages now
- Yet great drinkers - we know every one.
With talent I have been endowed
I defy heaven and earth with my truth
Who thinks of ancient sages now
- Yet great drinkers - we know every one.
With talent I have been endowed
Let stars gamble with the moon and sun
Who thinks of ancient sages now
- Yet great drinkers - we know every one.
As the sun and I set down the mountain
Am I followed by the moon?
I search for the paths that led here
Again to green mountain forests
And blue mountain mists.